Chapter 68. The blanket.
I have given no small attention to that not unvexed subject, the skin of the
whale. I have had controversies about it with experienced whaleman afloat and
learned naturalists assure. My original opinion remains unchanged, but it is only an opinion.
The question is, what and where is the skin of the whale? Already you know what
his blubber is. That blubber is something of the consistence of firm,
close grained beef, but tougher, more elastic, and compact, and ranges from 8
or 10 to 12 and 15 in in thickness.
Now, however preposterous it may at first seem to talk of any creature's
skin as being of that sort of consistence and thickness, yet in point
of fact, these are no arguments against such a presumption, because you cannot
raise any other dense enveloping layer from the whale's body but that same
blubber, and the outermost enveloping layer of any animal, if reasonably
dense, what can that be but the skin?
True, from the unmarred dead body of the whale, you may scrape off with your hand
an infinitely thin transparent substance somewhat resembling the thinnest shreds
of eisen glass, only it is almost as flexible and soft as satin, that is
previous to being dried when it not only contracts and thickens, but becomes
rather hard and brittle. I have several such dried bits which I use for marks in
my whale books. It is transparent, as I said before, and being laid upon the
printed page, I have sometimes pleased myself with fancying it exerted a
magnifying influence. At any rate, it is pleasant to read about whales through
their own spectacles, as you may say.
But what I am driving at here is this.
The same infinitely thin eisenglass substance which I admit invests the
entire body of the whale is not so much to be regarded as the skin of the
creature as the skin of the skin so to speak. For it were simply ridiculous to
say that the proper skin of the tremendous whale is thinner and more
tender than the skin of a newborn child.
But no more of this. Assuming the blubber to be the skin of the whale,
then when this skin, as in the case of a very large sperm whale, will yield the
bulk of 100 barrels of oil, and when it is considered that in quantity, or
rather weight, that oil in its express state is only three4s, and not the
entire substance of the coat. Some idea may hence be had of the enormousness of
that animated mass, a mere part of whose mere integument yields such a lake of
liquid as that. Reckoning 10 barrels to the ton, you have 10 tons for the net
weight of only 3/4 of the stuff of the whale's skin.
In life, the visible surface of the sperm whale is not the least among the
many marvels he presents. Almost invariably, it is all over, obliquely
crossed and recrossed, with numberless straight marks and thick array,
something like those in the finest Italian line engravings. But these marks
do not seem to be impressed upon the eisenlass substance above mentioned, but
seem to be seen through it, as if they were engraved upon the body itself. Nor
is this all, in some instances, to the quick observant eye, those linear marks,
as in a veritable engraving, but afford the ground for far other delineations.
These are hieroglyphical, that is, if you call those mysterious ciphers on the
walls of the pyramids hieroglyphics, then that is the proper word to use in
the present connection. By my retentive memory of the hieroglyphics upon one
sperm whale in particular, I was much struck with a plate representing the old
Indian characters chiseled on the famous hieroglyphic palisades on the banks of
the upper Mississippi. Like those mystic rocks too, the mystic marked whale
remains undecipherable.
This allusion to the Indian rocks reminds me of another thing. Besides all
the other phenomena which the exterior of the sperm whale presents, he not
seldom displays the back, and more especially his flanks, if faced in great
part of the regular linear appearance, by reason of numerous rude scratches,
altogether of an irregular random aspect. I should say that those New
England rocks on the sea coast, which Agassi imagines to bear the marks of
violent scraping contact with vast floating icebergs, I should say that
those rocks must not a little resemble the sperm whale in this particular. It
also seems to me that such scratches in the whale are probably made by hostile
contact with other whales, for I have most remarked them in the large
full-grown bulls of the species.
A word or two more concerning this matter of the skin or blubber of the
whale. It has already been said that it is stripped from him in long pieces
called blanket pieces. Like most sea terms, this one is very happy and
significant, for the whale is indeed wrapped up in his blubber, as in a real
blanket or counterpane, or as still better, an Indian poncho slipped over
his head and skirting his extremity. It is by reason of this cozy blanketing of
his body that the whale is unable to keep himself comfortable in all
weathers, in all seas, times, and tides.
What would become of a Greenland whale, say, in those shuddering icy seas of the
north, if unsupplied with his cozy cert?
True, other fish are found exceedingly brisk in those hyperboran waters, but
these, be it observed, are your coldblooded, lungless fish, whose very
bellies are refrigerators, creatures that warm themselves under the lee of an
iceberg, as a traveler in winter would bask before an inn fire. Whereas, like
man, the whale has lungs and warm blood, freeze his blood, and he dies. How
wonderful it is, then, except after explanation, that this great monster, to
whom corporeal warmth is as indispensable as it is to man, how
wonderful that he should be found at home, immersed to his lips for life in
those Arctic waters, where, when semen fall overboard, they are sometimes found
months afterward, perpendicularly frozen into the hearts of fields of ice, as a
fly is found glued in amber. But more surprising it is to know, as has been
proved by experiment, that the blood of a polar whale is warmer than that of a
Borneo negro in summer.
It does seem to me that herein we see the rare virtue of a strong individual
vitality, and the rare virtue of thick walls, and the rare virtue of interior spaciousness.
Oh man, admire and model thyself after the whale. Do thou too remain warm among
ice. Do thou too live in this world without being of it. Be cool at the
equator. Keep thy blood fluid at the pole. Like the great dome of St. Peter's
and like the great whale, retain, oh man, in all seasons a temperature of thine own.
But how easy and how hopeless to teach these fine things. Of erections, how few
are domed like St. Peters. Of creatures, how few vast as the whale.